Good morning, Canvas community, how are we doing this morning?
Man, I was excited about my message, but I got even more pumped through worship this morning.
So hopefully that is the same for you guys.
If we haven't had the privilege to meet yet, my name is Corey Smith and I happen to be part of the teaching team here at Canvas.
I've got a ton to cover this morning, so let's jump into it.
Let's pray and then we'll jump into it. Sound good, church?
Dear Heavenly Father, we come to you today fully expecting that you'll reveal something new to our hearts about you today, Lord.
That you'll bestow us with more courage and comfort as we apprentice and conform to the image of your son, Jesus.
Lord, I ask that you soften hearts today to our topic.
If it be from you, Lord, take me out of the way so the Spirit can speak through me.
I pray that the Father of our Lord Jesus, who gives us the spirit of wisdom today and reveals the more knowledge of him.
I pray that our hearts be enlightened so that we may live into the hope of our calling.
We thank you for the glorious inheritance promised to the saints.
Lord, for those hurting today, we ask for healing.
Lord, for those anxious today, we pray for peace.
We pray all of this for your glory and our neighbor's good.
And in the mighty name of Jesus, amen.
So, this week we'll be covering the question, why does God need to create a new heaven and a new earth?
Why couldn't he just do one or the other?
This week we'll sort of act as a part two to Ryan's sermon last week, which was this idea of present reality in light of the present truth.
Apocalypse, right?
The unveiling of what's going on behind the scenes to comfort the church and being able to see behind the veil.
If you haven't been here, we took some questions from the congregation and we prepared some sermons around those questions.
This is one of those sermons.
So, this week we'll be covering the topic of new heavens, new earth.
And we'll be sitting with this idea of why does God need to create a new heaven and new earth?
Why couldn't he just do one or the other?
And I'm going to paraphrase my whole sermon with this.
I don't know why God does anything, which is why he's God and I'm not, amen.
But this question is a great teaching point and it's something I'm very passionate about.
So, the Bible uses these ideas of heaven and earth as ways to express thoughts about God's realm and our realm.
Heaven for God's realm, earth for our realm.
So, my goal in answering this question today is why in the end does God need to create a new heaven and new earth?
Why couldn't he just do one or the other?
But let's set the stage here.
What does the Bible say about heaven?
What does the Bible say about earth?
And what part does all that play into this?
We all know what the earth is like, right?
We can work from experience there.
But I think we have some assumptions as a church of what heaven's like.
So, let's check those against the source text.
Pop culture, philosophies, entertainment love to disciple us on what heaven is like.
But is that how the Bible prepares and sets the stage for God's ultimate plan of restoration and reconciliation?
Is the ultimate plan for redemption to whisk us off to the sky, to a celestial candy land of sorts, where we all live in a mansion in the clouds and we all get everything we didn't get in this earthly life?
Where we all drive expensive cars, we all fish all day, we all golf all day, or whatever we want to do, somehow for the glory of God.
Some of my friends actually had a running joke for a while about a country song.
And it's kind of a, we weren't making fun of the song as much as we were the theology.
We used to say, decent song, terrible theology.
But the songs, the lyrics go like this.
Yeah, I believe them when they say you're in a better place.
You had a wild side, but you had amazing grace.
I know you're way off up in them clouds.
So, if you could still hear me right now, I hope you hit those gold streets on two wheels.
I hope your mansion in the sky has got a 10-acre field with some mud and some hubs you can lock in.
I think if we're all intellectually honest with ourselves, this weird picture of heaven that some people have in their minds doesn't actually fit in alignment with the God of the Bible.
And confession time.
This is my hesitation or even frustration sometimes when I talk about heaven or somebody talks to heaven with me.
Sometimes, not all the time.
Let me put that paraphrase out there.
Sometimes it feels like, when it's described, it feels like a Hallmark movie or a romantic comedy.
And if you like those things, great.
To me, they just feel cheap.
Right?
They don't unpack it.
They don't build to life the nuance and the complexities of our existence here.
And I, for one, just don't think God is cheap.
And I definitely don't think his plan for ultimate reconciliation is to evacuate us out of the world and to plop us in a cloudy place where we get everything we've ever wanted.
That just feels cheap.
Let me elaborate a bit more.
I know I'm poking a little bit.
Maria Shriver wrote in a book in 1999 called What's Heaven?
And I think this excerpt encapsulates Western thinking and even some in the church around this idea.
Heaven, Shriver says, heaven is somewhere you believe in.
It's a beautiful place where you can sit on soft clouds and talk to other people who are there.
At night, you can sit next to the stars, which are the brightest of anywhere in the universe.
If you're good throughout your life, then you get to go to heaven.
When your life is finished here on earth, God sends angels down to take you up to heaven to be with him.
And grandma's with me.
Most importantly, she taught me to believe in myself.
And she's watching us from up there.
And I fear, it's the caricature, but I feel this is what the world thinks.
And even some Christians just replace the line, if you're good throughout your life, then you get to go to heaven with.
If you believe in Jesus, then you get to go to heaven.
That would be the only real distinction about how Maria Shriver describes it.
See, I would strongly argue that this is not the biblical idea of heaven at all.
And if this is your first time joining us, you're welcome here.
Surprisingly to some people, the phrase going to heaven when you die is nowhere in the biblical text.
And many Christians assume that whenever the New Testament speaks of heaven, it refers to the place to which the save will go immediately after death.
But the language of the New Testament doesn't work that way.
Usually when heaven is referred to, it's referred to as the kingdom of heaven or even the kingdom of God.
This kingdom language that Jesus is referring to and preaching about is not our escape from this world into another one, but that God's sovereign rule is coming to earth as it is in heaven.
See, the roots of this misunderstanding go very deep, not least of all the philosophy of Plato that have seeped into our Christian worldview and that has taught us to devalue our bodies and devalue the present world as shameful or shabby.
Randy Alcorn calls this Christoplatonism, where we can have this Platonist idea, this philosophy, where our souls occupy our bodies like a hermit crab occupies a shell.
Christoplatonism is not a good thing.
It's actually a bad thing when we have a common philosophy that we transpose over the Scriptures.
Right?
For Christians, the question is not, do we have, and I may be stepping on some toes here, but bear with me.
For Christians, the question is not, do we have a soul or a body?
But the biblical fact is that we are both a soul and a body, a spiritual nature as well as a physical one.
God created us that way in a sort of cosmic unity.
It should never be an either or, but a both and.
Matthew Lee Anderson puts it well.
See, if we believe even subconsciously that the material world, this material world is inherently unspiritual, catch that.
If we believe this material world is unspiritual, just like when we separate body and soul, we will begin to ignore or even spiritualize the idea of resurrection.
Some people speak of a spiritual resurrection and not a physical one.
But just as a sunrise requires a sun, so too does resurrection require a body.
That's what resurrection means.
The resurrected Jesus assured his disciples in Luke 24, touch me and see me because a ghost doesn't have flesh or bones, as you can see I have.
Yet, right, I'm picking on us here, right?
Yet, even there's some evangelicals that imagine that we turn into ghosts.
This is the danger.
The very thing that we turn into ghosts, the very thing Jesus reassured his disciples he was not.
This is the danger of separating the spiritual and physical aspects of our creative world.
The good news is, this is not the narrative of the Scripture.
We are not destined for a disembodied existence.
In fact, the pictures of heaven in Revelation, especially Revelation 4 and 5, which Ryan preached about last week,
where the 24 elders are casting their crowns before the throne of heaven,
beside the throne of God and the Lamb, beside the sea of glass,
is not a picture of the last day where all the redeemed are in an ethereal heaven at last,
but instead is a picture of present reality, the invasion of the heavenly dimension into our present life.
Heaven in the Bible is not just a future destiny.
But it is the other hidden dimension of our ordinary lives.
God's dimension, if you'd like.
God made heaven and earth in Genesis 1, and at last he will remake and join them both together forever.
See, when we come to this picture, the last two chapters in the Bible,
we don't find ransomed souls making their way to a disembodied heaven,
but rather we find the new Jerusalem coming down from heaven to earth,
uniting the two spheres in an everlasting embrace, the way God designed them to be.
God never changes, but heaven and earth will.
Randy Alcorn says this in an article I read,
we err when we confuse the present pre-resurrection heaven with the future post-resurrection heaven
that God will bring down to the new earth.
The present heaven is far better, according to Philippians 1.23,
than our lives under the curse of sin and suffering.
Upon death, we will be at home with the Lord, says 2 Corinthians 5.8.
But my point is, wonderful though as it may be,
we should not think of this present heaven as if it were our ultimate home.
The best is yet to come.
An eternal and delightful life,
worshiping and serving forever,
incarnate Jesus on the new and redeemed earth.
See, God made us both spirit and body the first time, right?
You and I are spirit and body.
Why do we think that plan changed?
See, what we say about death and resurrection
gives shape and color to everything else.
If we're not careful, we offer merely a hope that is no longer a surprise,
no longer able to transform lives and communities in the present,
no longer generated by the resurrection of Jesus of himself
and looking forward to a new heaven, new earth.
The resurrection of Jesus changed the way the disciples saw their lives here.
It transformed them.
And I believe it still has that same transforming power today.
See, when they saw the resurrected Jesus,
the promise and hope that we should live in,
in the same way their tomb was empty,
So too will our graves be.
Our bodies, our physical bodies, albeit glorified,
will rise to worship from those graves
in an earthly, fully redeemed,
in an earth, fully redeemed with God as its rightful king.
See, I prayed this sermon wasn't seen as contentious,
but instead inspiring for all of you as it was for me
when I dove into this topic.
New heaven, new earth, resurrected bodies,
the God of the universe dealing final blows to enemies like sin,
injustice, and ultimately death itself.
Correcting and redeeming plan A,
which God is always in the business of doing.
See, where we don't sidestep our problems
and we teleport to a world somewhere else,
but where we have front row seats
to see God confront those problems head on,
either with our participation as the church
or him alone striking the final blow like only he can do.
See, the Scripture, in fact,
teaches things about the future resurrected life
that most Christians and almost all non-Christians
have never heard of.
I've prepared some heavy Bible reading today,
so without further ado, let's jump into the text.
We're going to start in Revelation 21,
and we are going to read all the way to Revelation 22, 5,
so hang on.
Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth,
for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away,
and the sea was no more.
I also saw the holy city, the new Jerusalem,
coming down out of heaven from God,
prepared like a bride adorned for her husband.
I listened to a sermon by Timothy Keller
where he says,
this changed my theology about heaven,
these two words, coming down.
Then I heard a loud voice from the throne saying,
look, God's dwelling is with humanity,
and he will live with them.
They will be his disciples,
and God himself will be with them,
and will be their God.
He will wipe every tear from their eyes.
Death will be no more.
Grief, crying, and pain will be no more,
because the previous things have passed away.
Then the one seated on the throne said,
look, I am making everything new.
He also said, right, because these words are faithful and true.
Then he said to me, it is done.
I am the alpha and the omega,
the beginning and the end,
and I will freely give to the thirsty
from the spring of the waters of life.
The one who conquers will inherit these things,
and I will be his God,
and he will be my son.
But the cowards,
faithless,
detestable,
murderers,
sexually immoral,
sorcerers,
idolaters,
and all liars,
their share will be in the lake
that burns with fire and sulfur,
which is the second death.
Then one of the seven angels
who had held the seven bowls
filled with the last,
with the seven plagues,
came and spoke with me,
come,
and I will show you the bride,
the wife of the lamb.
And then he carried me away in the spirit
to a great high mountain
and showed me the holy city,
Jerusalem,
coming down out of heaven from God.
Arrayed with God's glory,
her radiance was a precious jewel
like a jasper stone,
clear as crystal.
The city had massive high walls
with 12 gates,
12 angels were at the gates
and the name of the 12,
12 tribes of Israel's son
were inscribed on the gates.
There were three gates on the east,
three gates on the north,
three gates on the south,
and three gates on the west.
The city had 12 foundations
and the 12 names of the 12 apostles
of the lamb were on the foundation.
The one who spoke with me
had a golden measuring rod
to measure the city,
its gates,
and its walls.
The city had laid out in the square,
I'm going to skip through that.
Let's start in 22.
You guys feel free to read that.
Just for the sake of time,
I don't want to keep you here all day.
Verse 22,
I did not see a temple in it
because the Lord God,
the Almighty,
and the Lamb are its temple.
The city does not need
the sun or the moon
to shine on it
because the glory of God
illuminates it
and its lamp is the Lamb.
The nations will walk by its light
and the kings of the earth
will bring their glory into it.
Its gates will never close by day
because it will never be night there.
They will bring the glory
and honor
of the nations into it.
Nothing unclean
will ever enter it
nor anyone who does
what is detestable or false
but only those written
in the Lamb's book of life.
Then he showed me
a river of the water of life,
clear as crystal,
flowing from the throne of God
and the Lamb
down the middle
of the city's main street.
The tree of life
was on each side of the river
bearing 12 kinds of fruit
producing its fruit
every month.
The leaves of the tree
are for the healing
of the nations
and there will no longer
be any curse.
The throne of God
and the Lamb
will be in the city
and the servants
will worship Him.
They will see His face
and His name
will be on their foreheads.
Night will be no more.
People will not need
the light of a lamp
or light of the sun
because the Lord
will give them light
and they will reign
forever and ever.
See, now we can enter
into this conversation
all being on the same page
where we see
this new creation,
this final state
where heaven and earth
are recombined
in their perfected state.
Now what I want to do
is give you like
a 10 minute overview
of the Bible,
maybe a little bit more
than that,
and the narrative
that brought us here.
I won't be able
to cover everything today
so be gracious with me
and hopefully
that will encourage you
to do your own
biblical study.
So like I said earlier,
a distorted view of heaven
can make this whole
biblical narrative
feel like an evacuation plan
and I don't think
that's how God intends us
to read it at all.
See God,
I really like this,
God's plan of creation
is not the cosmic version
of the Vietnam War.
Sit with that.
God's plan of creation
is not the cosmic version
of the Vietnam War.
See where he has to,
if you're not familiar
with the Vietnam War,
where he has to get us
out of here
because there's no chance
for victory
and it's just a waste
of time and resources.
No.
My God is mighty
to win.
He doesn't retreat.
See this is the heart
behind the theological term
Christus Victor
which is Latin for
Christ the Victor.
The Gospel Coalition
defines Christus Victor
in this way.
Christus Victor
is the element
of the atoning work
of Christ
that emphasizes
the triumph
of Christ
over the evil powers
of the world
through which he rescues
and redeemed
or rescues his people
and establishes
a new relationship
between God
and the world.
The fall of man
is not the fall
of Saigon
and God says
well they messed that up
on the plan B I guess.
No.
God's plan
has always been
plan A
and it always will be.
God has
and is
reclaiming
his creation
for ultimately
his glory
and our good.
Let me ask you
this question.
When your house
is a wreck
do you burn
it down
and move
somewhere else?
No.
Right?
What do you do?
You clean it up.
Typically it's my kids
making my house
a wreck
so I burn it down
every five minutes.
But like
think about it
like that.
If your house
is a wreck
because your kids
messed it up
we don't do that.
This is God's plan
to clean up
and redeem
his good creation
so that he can come
and dwell with us.
So that's
God's plan
of a redeemed creation.
Let's look at
Revelation 22.2
again for some
callback clues.
If we're going
an overview
let's get some
callback clues.
The tree of life
was on each side
of the river
bearing 12 kinds
of fruit
producing fruit
every month.
The leaves
of the tree
are for the healing
of the nation.
The leaves
of the tree of life
are for what?
You can
the healing
of the nation.
The forgetting
of the nations?
of the atrocities
that the nations
did to the people
that were under them?
No.
The healing.
God is reconciling
all the injustices
that we
as mankind
have perpetrated
and experienced.
The trees
the leaves
of the tree of life
are for the healing
of the nations.
That tidbit was free.
What I want you
to look at
is this idea
of the tree of life.
Where is the last place
we saw the tree of life?
In the garden
right in Genesis.
So let's start
there.
Genesis 1.1
In the beginning
God created
what?
Does that sound familiar?
Genesis 1.26
Then God said
let us make man
in our image
according to our likeness
they will rule
the fish of the sea
the birds of the sky
the livestock
the whole earth
and the creatures
that crawl
on the earth.
Verse 27
So God created man
in his own image
and he created him
in the image
of God.
He created them
male and female.
God created mankind
to live upon the earth.
This was our domain
a place where God
gave us responsibility
to steward
and have dominion
over.
This is home
for humanity.
Verse 28
God blessed them
and said to them
be fruitful
and multiply
fill the earth
and subdue it.
This is the divine commission.
Psalm 8 reinforces
this idea
for the sake of time
I took that out
of my sermon
but Psalm 8
for my note takers
read that.
Psalm 8 reinforces
this idea
that God made humans
to rule over
the works of his hands
that he put all things
under their feet
with various forms
of animal life
as examples
of what is under
the feet of humans.
In all these
creational texts
the movement we see
is what we might call
missional
from God
right
via humans
outward towards the earth
from God
via humans
outward towards the earth.
The fundamental
human task
we were created for
is the responsible
exercise of power
on God's behalf
over the domain
he put us in
our earthly environment.
J. Richard Middleton
says this on the topic
perhaps the most
significant of all
is that the biblical God
does not hoard power
as a sovereign ruler
of the cosmos
instead
he gladly assigns
humanity a share
in ruling the earth
as his representatives.
God does not
micromanage the world
but
instead
fully expects
human beings
made in the divine
image to contribute
to the developing
beauty
and complexity
of earthly
life.
In verse 31
of Genesis 1
we'll see that God
looks over his creation
and calls it what?
This is a trick question
so think about it.
Very good.
So I think
this is something
we overlook
when we
revert back
to God's cosmic
version of Vietnam.
I think we overlook
this
mindset
that God
the creator
of the universe
looks back
on the sixth day
and calls it what?
All right?
Good
but these humans
are going to
screw it up?
No.
He calls it
very good.
John Schneider
writes this in his book
The Good Affluence.
This creation
that God
majestically
called forth
into being
is good.
It is good
in its individual
parts
It is good
as a whole
as an integrated
system
In fact
in this
integrative
cosmic sense
the text
informs us
that God
declared it
to be
very good.
This was it guys
This is plan A
God
created the heavens
and the earth
and all the things
in it
the plants
the animals
everything
then he
moves on
to the sixth day
where God
creates humanity
to steward
all of his creation
and to have
dominion over it
Then what happens
on the seventh day?
God rest us
right?
He looks over
his masterpiece
that he created
So what happened
to this good
this good plan?
How many of us?
Us, right?
Well, kind of us
We are not
intrinsically good
Sin enticed us
and we invited it in
Let's look at
Genesis 3
Eve
tempted by the serpent
seizes autonomy
for herself
in the form of a fruit
from the one tree
that God implicitly
told them
was off limit
the tree of the knowledge
of good and evil
Eve then entices
Adam to eat as well
through this
collaborative disobedience
not just Eve
where mankind
will now seize
or take
that autonomy
from God
where we would decide
what is good and evil
not God
See, this breach
of covenant
had consequences
Let's take a time
I won't unpack
all those consequences
right now
but I will touch on one
typically the one
that has to do
with my sermon
so
we're going to
touch on that one
Sin exiled us
from the garden
the one singular
space
sphere of God's
and man's space
were now
separate
and distinct
Let's look at
heaven and earth
separate
thank you
guys are on today
I only gave them
like 150 slides
today
so they're in
good shape
this place
where God
would not
cohabit with sin
in his good creation
he would not do it
let's look at
Genesis 3
22 through 24
the Lord
God said
since man
has become
like one of us
knowing both
good and evil
he must not
reach out
and take
or seize
from the tree
of life
and eat
and live
forever
so the Lord
God sent him
away from
the garden
of Eden
to work
the ground
from which
he was taken
he drove
the man out
and stationed
cherubim
and the flaming
whirling sword
east of the
garden of Eden
to guard
the way
to the tree
of life
after their
disobedience
Adam and Eve
were left
to their own
desire
they entered
into a world
that was
separated
by their sin
a world
of pain
hardship
thorns
thistles
and the ultimate
enemy
death
that is in
separation
from God's
realm
that is
holy
and just
and full
of life
verse 23
is a sad
commentary
of what God
had to do
with mankind
the pinnacle
of his creation
Adam and Eve
were taken out
of the paradise
of God
and placed
in the world
at large
to cultivate
the cursed
ground
the very
dust
from which
Adam was
formed
because of
their desire
our desire
for power
and autonomy
and God's
desire
for humanity
not to be
eternally
separated
from him
because of
our sin
but
good news
still abounds
God is still
in the business
of forgiveness
and redemption
and the fact
that the tree
of life
appears again
in Revelation
means that
the beginning
plan
is still
his plan
again
this is not
God's version
of the Vietnam
War
I'm not so
literal to say
that it needs
to be a tree
that exists
that has the
secret to
immortality
but what I
think the
biblical authors
intended us
to think
and feel
is that
the tree
of life
is a
symbol
a symbol
of a
life
alongside
God
in relationship
in community
and in communion
with him
where our
proximity
to him
bestows our
gift of
eternal life
Paul's first
letter to
Timothy
codenamed
1 Timothy
through 16
exercises this
idea
that no one
is immortal
besides God
himself
God will bring
this about
in his own
time
he is the
blessed
and only
sovereign
the king
of kings
the Lord
of lords
who alone
is immortal
and who
lives in
an unapproachable
light
whom no man
has seen
or can see
to him
be honor
and eternal
power
amen
Paul goes
on to
write this
to Timothy
in 2 Timothy
1 10
that this
has now
been made
evident
through the
appearing
of our
savior
Jesus
Christ
who
abolished
death
and has
brought
life
and
immortality
to light
through
the gospel
the most
famous
I'll stick
to this
claim
the most
famous
verse
in all
the world
John 3
for God
so loved
the world
in this
way
he gave
his one
and only
son
that everyone
who believes
in him
will not
perish
but what
have
eternal
life
eternality
is a gift
from God
not something
naturally innate
about us
and especially
not something
for us to
reach out
and seize
for ourselves
God wants
us to be
able to dwell
in his
presence
pure
and unblemished
how will
we accomplish
this task
you might ask
I repeat
this is not
God's version
of the
Vietnam War
this idea
of God
retaining a
stronghold
in his
creation
permeates
through the
Scriptures
if you
read them
in that
way
he promises
not to
leave us
as orphans
any
attempt
of humanity
to reach
God
is thwarted
but the
plan
of God
is to
fully
envelop
humanity
which is
ultimately
fulfilled
in the
final piece
of new
creation
new
heavens
earth
so how
does God
retain a
stronghold
in creation
through avenues
like the
tabernacle
the tent
of meetings
where the
presence of God
chose to dwell
among the
Israelites
though
because of
the curse
there are
stipulations
right
one of the
cool things
we covered
in our last
passages
class was
this idea
of the
book of
Leviticus
who here
loves the
book of
Leviticus
I'll stop
you guys
are liars
everybody
loves
Leviticus
but this
idea in
the book
of Leviticus
it gives
us criteria
that God
demands
if we
in the
curse
wish to
be in
his
presence
because
the
presence
of God
is pure
love
holiness
and light
I love
this
I heard
this a long
time ago
and I love
this idea
if we
can't look
directly at
the sun
and it's
91.976
million miles
away
what makes
you think
you're going
to waltz
right into
the presence
of the
creator
so the
book of
Leviticus
seeks to
accomplish
just that
how do
we as
humans
how do
they as
the Israelites
stand in
the presence
of God
Leviticus
starts out
in verse
one by
the presence
of God
speaking to
Moses
from the
tent of
meetings
inside out
right
the next
book
numbers
God is
speaking to
Moses
in the
tent of
meetings
he's
invited
fickle
he
requires
things
to be
done
and
to be
done
according
to his
will
all the
sacrifice
and purification
laws
the Israelites
had to do
in Leviticus
ultimately
worked so
that they
could be
in the
presence
of God
so the
tent of
meetings
is actually
separated
into two
sections
right
the holy
of holies
and the
holy place
a thick
veil
separated
the two
rooms
are we
picking up
on this
veil
imagery
right
the priests
were allowed
to occupy
the holy
space
but only the
high priest
once a year
was permitted
to enter
the holy
of holies
this holy
represented
God's presence
in space
among the
camp of the
Israelites
and it
actually if I
had a cool
picture of it
the tabernacle
sat in the
midst of the
camp in the
middle of the
camp
this tabernacle
is God's
or not God's
this tabernacle
is a mobile
garden of Eden
embroidered with
fantastic tapestry
which alluded
to a time
and place
where heaven
and earth
met
where they
were combined
this is the
hope
this is where
heaven now
meets earth
this is the
stronghold
reminder to the
Israelites
that God
created the heavens
and the earth
and he never
will abandon it
actually quite the
opposite
he chose to
make his
presence known
to them
inside the
tent he chose
to lead them
through the
wilderness
this is his
stronghold
within his
creation
and his
desire to
see it
fully justified
the tabernacle
is the place
where heaven
met earth
and God
chose Israel
to be his
representatives
in doing that
but the
tabernacle
always had a
temporary element
to it
I mean the
tent traveled
through the
wilderness
with the
Israelites
right
like who
has a
tent
who travels
with it
in the desert
for 40
years
and it's
like
primo
no but
eventually
this master
plan
like
comes more
into view
where heaven
meets earth
becomes more
permanent
with the
construction
of Solomon's
temple
in Jerusalem
see Solomon's
temple would
have three
main rooms
the forecourt
the outer
sanctum
and the
inner shrine
which is
the holy
of holies
again this
large veil
would separate
the outer
sanctum
from the
holy of
holies
where the
presence of
God
chose to
dwell
above the
mercy seat
once a
year
the high
priest
would again
go in
and atone
for the
sins
of the
people
again this
artistry
and imagery
of the
garden
was emblazoned
on the
temple
this idea
where this
is the
place
heaven
meets
earth
the only
language
that they
had for
that
was what
come on
people
stay awake
with me
Eden
this is
what they
had for
this was
Eden
the biblical
narrative
goes through
cycles where
the people
of Israel
where they're
obedient to
God
they disobey
they're judged
they repent
God restores
them all
while God
never forgetting
the promise
that he made
to the
people
we can go
to the next
slide now
guys in the
midst of this
dire situation
of brokenness
after a long
and complex
history of
redemption
God's saving
action culminates
in the coming
of Jesus
Christ
this Messiah
who is
described in
the New
Testament as
God's son
the incarnate
word
the
ultimate
imago
day or
image bearer
of God
the one
who
completely
manifests
God's
character
and presence
in the
full range
of his
very
earthly
human
life
again
God
coming
to us
for our
salvation
this is seen
through the
words of the
gospel of John
let's look at
John 1 14
where John
says
the word
became flesh
and dwelt
among us
that word
dwelt
is the
same
word
in the
Greek
as
tabernacle
Jesus
tabernacled
among us
think about
this idea
of Jesus
as the
tabernacle
this place
where
heaven
now
eats
earth
like we
talked about
earlier
the tabernacle
was a sort
of temporary
dwelling place
and Jesus
would only
be with us
a short
time to
accomplish
his
mission
Jesus
didn't
evacuate
his followers
out of
this world
the moment
they believed
in him
quite the
opposite
he called
them to
a higher
purpose
here
on
earth
he taught
them to
pray like
this
our
father
who art
hallowed
be thy
name
thy
kingdom
will be
done
where
and ultimately
his mission
culminated at
the cross
of Calvary
this promise
comes into
view with
the crucifixion
of Jesus
this picture
that the
God
incarnate
became
the sin
of the
world
for us
so that
we might
be
restored
to
the
father
let's
look at
Matthew
through
Jesus
cried
out again
in a
loud
voice
and he
gave
up
his
spirit
suddenly
the
curtain
of the
sanctuary
was torn
in two
from top
to bottom
the earth
quaked
and the
rocks
were split
what
curtain
or veil
is Matthew
speaking
of
the
holy of
holies
this
is the
undoing
this
action
of Jesus
is the
undoing
of the
separation
of God
and man
now culminated
in the
person and
death of
Jesus
the writer of
Hebrews says
that we now
have a new
high priest
Jesus
through Jesus
the stronghold
that God
has created
and creation
begins to break
through in
bigger and
miraculous ways
after his
resurrection and
before his
ascension to the
throne of heaven
we see in
Matthew 28
starting in verse
16 where
Jesus gives
the great
commission
the eleven
disciples traveled
to Galilee
to the mountain
where Jesus
had directed
them
when they saw
him they
worshipped
but some
doubted
Jesus came
near and
said all
authority has
been given
to me
where just
in heaven
on heaven
and on
earth
so knowing
that all
authority both
in our realm
and in God's
realm is now
Jesus says go
therefore and make
disciples of all
nations baptizing
them in the
name of the
father and
the son and
the Holy Spirit
teaching them to
observe everything
I have commanded
you and remember
I am with you
always even to
the end of the
age through the
life death and
resurrection of
Jesus heaven
reclaimed an
even greater
foothold on
earth how can I
say that with
confidence obviously
the words of
Jesus I'll stick to
those but don't
worry we'll keep
reading John 14
12 truly I tell
you the one who
believes in me
will also do the
works that I do
and he will
even do greater
works than these
because I am
going to the
father like
is anybody sat
with that verse
and they're like
man really like
greater works than
Jesus remember
Jesus is talking
to the disciples
here and I
think he's speaking
to the church
indirectly but if
you continue reading
the promise is
based on the
promise of the
Holy Spirit that
through Jesus
going back to
the father and
the Holy Spirit
being with us the
church will now
accomplish things
that for and
with Jesus
heaven and
earth let's go
to the Pentecost
slide acts to
verse one
when the day of
Pentecost had
arrived they were
all together in one
place suddenly a
loud sound like
that of a violent
rushing wind came
from where
heaven
y'all are acting
like I trick
question you on
everyone
although it is
embarrassing when
you shout out the
wrong thing I will
acknowledge that
and it filled the
whole house where
they were staying
they saw tongues
like flames of
fire that separated
and rested on each
of them and they
were all filled with
the Holy Spirit
look at first
Corinthians 6 19
and 20
don't you know
that your body is
a temple of the
Holy Spirit in
whom you have
from God you are
not your own for
you were bought
with a price so
glorify God with
your bodies does
this feel shabby
or shameful
no glorify God
with your bodies
Paul says that we
are the temples of
the Holy Spirit
remember that the
tabernacle is the
place where heaven
met earth
temporarily the
temple is the
place now where
heaven meets
earth we are now
the permanent place
in which God is
working we as
apprentices of Lord
Jesus are now his
stronghold in this
world we are now
the place where
heaven meets
earth this
language of
heaven meeting
earth gets
picked up by the
apostle Paul when
he uses the
language of new
creation which I
love because it
contrasted with old
creation let's look
at second
Corinthians 5 17
therefore if
anyone is in
Christ he is a
new creation the
old has passed
away see the new
has come see if
anyone is in
Christ not only can
they rest secure in
the world to come
with Jesus they are
now part of his
new creation here
and now some
would even say
that the he is
isn't in the
Greek so we tend
to individualize
that what Paul is
literally saying
then if the he is
isn't in there
anyone in Christ
new creation no
longer a part of
the old fallen
creation this is
why Paul goes on
to say in verse
20 and 21
therefore we are
ambassadors of
Christ since God
is making his
appeal through us
we plead on
Christ's behalf
be reconciled to
God he made the
one who did not
know sin to become
sin for us so
that in him we
might become the
righteousness of
God brothers and
sisters we are no
longer a part of the
world system we now
belong to the kingdom
of God the kingdom
of heaven the place
where God resides
church we in the
here and now should
be representing the
place where heaven
meets earth I've
done a really good
job of not quoting
into right but I'm
not perfect Tom
Wright captures this
idea and the whole
thought God created
human beings to be
his vice rulers in
the beginning to be
his vice rulers over
the world that is at
part that is at least
part of what it is
meant that humans
were made in God's
image this image is
like an angled
mirror reflecting God's
wise and caring love
into the world
bringing order and
fruitfulness to the
garden where the
humans were placed
that project was of
course tragically
twisted with human
arrogance and sin
we get this last
but that plan has
never been rescinded
my time is closing
in I'm doing my I'm
going to do my best
to land this plane
the apostle Paul wraps
all this idea around
new creation around
one thing the
centrality of Christ
look at Colossians 1
15 through 23 he
Christ is the image
of the invisible God
the firstborn over all
of creation for
everything was created
by him in where
heaven and earth the
visible and the
invisible whether
thrones or dominions
or rulers or
authorities all things
have been created
through him and for
him he is before all
things and by him all
things are held
together he is also
the head of the body
the church he is the
beginning the first
born of the dead so
that he might have
first place in
everything for God was
pleased to have his
fullness dwell in him
and through him to
reconcile everything
back to himself
whether the things on
earth or things in
heaven by making
peace through his
blood shed on the
cross once you were
alienated and hostile
in your minds as
expressed in your evil
actions but now he
has reconciled you by
his physical body
through his death to
present you holy
faith faultless and
blameless before him
if indeed you remain
grounded and steadfast in
the faith you are not
shifted away from the
hope of the gospel that
you heard this gospel has
been proclaimed under all
creation in all creation
under heaven and I
Paul have become a
servant of it so
Corey practically how do
we live this out how do I
share a gospel that's
more than do you know
if you die are you
going to heaven it's
hard I'll admit it's
harder it's more
complex but it's not
cheap because let's be
honest the Bible doesn't
have a ton to say about
what happens after we die
it's quite foggy but I
believe that the love of
God supersedes any power
that death has but we
get a clear picture of
God's beginning plan God's
ultimate plan with the
centrality of that plan in
Christ my recommendation
when talking to someone
who is curious about this
Christian life start with
physical resurrection start
with Jesus's resurrection
and our promised one so
we've made the Gospels of
Jesus all about like going
to heaven I'm pretty sure I
can make the argument that
the Gospels climaxes is not
about going to some
spiritual heaven but
instead Christ the image of
the invisible God coming to
earth to show us how to
live and to show us that
God ultimately has the
power over death sin and
over all of creation
Paul says this in first
Corinthians 15 that if
Christ didn't rise from the
dead then we are still in
our sins I mean that if
Christ didn't rise we'd all
be eternally separated from
the father the giver of
life Paul doesn't say if
there is no heaven to go to
then the Christian life is
futile no he said if there
is no resurrection of the
dead then the hope of
Christianity is just an
illusion and we're the
most to be pitied for
placing our faith in
Christ Paul has no lasting
hope in a heaven that is
merely for spirits or what
has been coined the
intermediate state right
where we go immediately
after we die or the
pre-resurrection state no
Paul has a hope in a
redeemed heaven and earth
where the dead in Christ i.e.
their glorified bodies are
raised and perishable just
as Jesus's body was raised
and perishable where God
dwells among his people in
a restored Eden this is the
final state that Paul
expresses hope in which is
the final state or the
post-resurrection state so I've
hope I have hope in the
resurrection of the dead not
in a weird spiritual sense but
in a very physical one where
my body will be raised from
the grave and perishable and
glorified just as my saviors
did as my my grandparents
bodies my children's bodies
my friends bodies perfected
and glorifying God in a
perfected glorified creation
the way it was always
intended to be remember this
is not God's version of
Vietnam where he needs to
evacuate us out instead he
comes to us and redeems this
world that is and always has
been God's plan a for his
creation to dwell with us and
him to for him to dwell with
us and us with him in a
perfected state in his
created place what then
will it look like for the
church now as heaven invades
more of earth remember
present reality in light of
future hope the good news is
that the resurrected king of
the universe has come to
usher in the kingdom of God
and make it available for all
who repent and believe to
unpack those biblical terms
repent and believe they mean
those of you Jesus came for
those of you who are willing to
rethink and to turn from
everything you think will
lead to the good life and
put their faith and trust and
allegiance in the life
teachings of a resurrected
savior George Eldon Ladd
coined the phrase the
already not yet kingdom of
heaven but the but Jesus's
birth life death resurrection
ascension opened up a portal
pointed a signpost or unveiled
the truth of how to live under the
kingdom of God now in the
anticipation of the whole
world we can do that church he
has invited us in to live under
his reign now as an
anticipation of what will
come this is the aim of the
church to live as a people
under the reign of heaven in
anticipation for the time the
whole world will do the same
that can give off smells of
utopianism but it's not
not implementing it it's living in
hope of it we're in the
already not yet kingdom of God
where Christ is ruling and
reigning but earth as we know
it has not fully welcomed her
true king where we look back at
the already of his first coming
and we have hope in the not yet of
his second where we look forward
to judgment day that sounds weird
not the bad kind of judgment but
the good kind of judgment like
justice we want justice God we
want you to bring justice to your
created place
this crucial balance of the
already not yet that our faith
requires the disappointment
suffering and the pain that
characterizes this present world is
held in dynamic tension with the
future glory that's yet to come
this is where the church lives in a
world where the dynamic tension of
sorrow and joy we live out our life
with Jesus we live with one foot in
the sphere of earth where we feel
sorrow but very realistically we live
in with one foot in the sphere of
heaven where we have joy I hope I've
said it I hope I said enough to make
it clear that the mission of the
church is nothing more or less than
the outworking in the power of the
spirit Jesus's bodily resurrection and
thus the anticipation of the time
when God will fill the earth with his
glory and transform the old heavens and
the old earth into new and raise his
children from the dead to populate and
rule over the redeemed world that he
has made if this is so then the church
can step into difficult spaces where
this mindset where spaces where real
people live spaces where real
communities happen spaces where
difficult decisions are made where
schools rescue mission angel trees
what point to the already of the kingdom
of God but where places like war and
prisons point to the not yet
thus the church takes sacred space
seriously like heaven meeting earth
Kelly if you want to come on up if
you're not already on your way
seriously I'm almost done seriously as a
not as a retreat or an escape from
this world but as a another avenue or
invasion into it and we'll go
straight from worshiping where we as
the church will go straight from
worshiping in the sanctuary to caring
for the poor the widow and the orphan
to live with the present reality of a
world ravaged by sin with a fervent
hope that Christ will redeem it knowing
that the world the whole world the whole
creation is to be redeemed as God's
once again where heaven and earth are
recombined we must seek to be
ambassadors to a world that does not
take the fact that Jesus that does
not take ambassadors to a world that
does not take the fact seriously that
Jesus is Lord over heaven and earth
the world is fully comfortable with
Jesus being king of heaven the world
is not comfortable with the idea that
Jesus is also Lord over earth where we
can plead with people as Paul says to
be reconciled to God but no people are
often cynical that if we take the
commands of Jesus seriously people
will say again and again to the
church to get back to your proper
mission proper business of saving
souls that radical distortion of the
Christian hope belongs exactly with a
quietism that leaves the world as it is
and thus allows evil to proceed
unchecked N.T. Wright says this about
the mission of the church I have argued
that a mission shaped church must have
its mission shaped by its hope that
the genuine Christian hope rooted in
the resurrection of Jesus is the hope
for God's renewal of all things for his
overcoming of corruption decay and
death for his filling of the whole
cosmos with his love and grace his
power and his glory church when I say
I'm passionate about this it's because
this mindset has changed the way I look
at being a Christian for me there's a
weight and a responsibility placed on
me here and now to proclaim and live
into the good news that the kingdom of
heaven is here we are the priesthood
all of us not just the ones up here on
stage but you to your co-workers to
your family to strangers to them you
represent Jesus now you are the place
where heaven meets earth this view has
consequences right just don't strive to
see souls saved but rather instead rather
see a whole person transformed a whole
body and soul transformed to the image of
Jesus to live into the reality that God is
king now not just later and with each
proclamation of the gospel in response
to it the kingdom of heaven grows larger
and the Holy Spirit begins in dwelling just
another person what I like to call building
for the God's kingdom I can disciple my
family and others that God's plan wasn't to
take us from this earth but rather make us
agents of transformation to this earth
before this earth anticipating the day the
earth shall see the full knowledge of the
Lord as the waters cover the sea that's why
I get pumped for baptisms not in the sense
of yeah I need to go to heaven when they
die no but that now they too have been
reconciled to God and God's kingdom grows
even larger I want death and injustice
destroyed God chose us to do that the God
of the universe chose us to bear a light to
be a salt to live in his commandments so
that our neighbors would say wow what a God
they serve they've laid aside the desires
that the world says are a success or what
leads to the good life instead they've
chosen to pick up the mantle of someone
they claim is king and live in such a way
as if he was here right now I can disciple
my children to lean into what God desires
from us not from a moral superiority
complex or the scary God in the sky wants
to hit him with a stick no but that God loves
us enough to partner with us with him to
bring about his kingdom on earth as it is
in heaven and God cares deeply about our
bodies and what we do with them we are his
temple I want to see justice prevail I want
to see poverty eradicated I want to see
cancer disappear I want to see death
destroyed once and for all I want to know
what it is to live in God's good creation
without sin pain and death that's the hope
that we are ambassadors of Christ citizens
of heaven the place where everyone sees heaven
meeting earth and wants to taste and see
that the Lord is good have we heard the
phrase don't be so heavenly minded that
you're of no earthly good I've seen that so
the phrase has bearing but it has bearing when
we trash our rivers for earthly riches where
we don't see the divine value in every human
life no matter the color of their skin no
matter their country of origin or their
propensity to help grow our GDP what we're
all worried about is making sure that the
formula of prayer is right so when you die
your good or so that we can brag about the
sides of our church I don't care about
those things I don't want discipleship to
take a back seat but in this holistic view
of heaven and earth that we just talked
about I don't think it's possible to be
too heavenly minded that you're of no
earthly good because instead of getting out
of here you're partnering with God in his
kingdom here and now which looks an
awful lot like loving your neighbors as
yourselves caring for the poor the
widow and the orphan it's a scary thing
I'm still wrestling with the weight of it
following me as I learn to follow Jesus
dare I say turning our swords into plowshares
I could build a I've used this analogy this
week and I thought it was pertinent for the
whole congregation I can build a birdhouse
really it's not that hard but I'd rather build a
birdhouse with my sons what take five times as
long absolutely not because they're not
because they're good at it not because
they're master craftsmen but they but then I
love participation nothing God does too I think the
people of God are often the biggest stumbling block to
God's ultimate mission I know I am so you guys
could sit with that if you want but God still
chooses to partner with us to see his plan fully
enacted.
I hope I've done this question justice today, church.
Why does God need to create a new heaven and earth?
Why doesn't he just create one or the other?
I believe the biblical narrative points to the fact that God's original plan has always
included the two in an everlasting embrace, not one over the other.
They were never supposed to be separate, but always together.
God dwelling with us as our king, as we worship and partner with him as the truest vocation
of humanity, bearing perfectly this divine image.
In the theme of the already not yet, and I didn't even do it.
Can somebody grab me a communion cup?
In the theme of the already not yet, is this gluten free?
Communion is the perfect picture of God's plan enacted while we have light in the future
fruition of the things to come.
The present reality and light of things to come.
We hurt now.
Sickness, death, pain are still among us now, but we have a hope that God will finally give
us justice to all the things that he hates.
We practice open communion here at Canvas, which means I'm not going to police whether or not
you can take communion.
But I would ask you to self-evaluate before doing it.
Before doing communion together with Jesus, I would ask you, have you submitted your life
to the Lordship of Jesus?
Where the Holy Spirit now dwells and dwells you as a temple of the living God.
Where you partner with God to see his kingdom spread over the earth.
The answer is no.
I'd ask you to refrain from communion.
But I'm going to make myself available up here if you have questions.
I have questions about becoming part of this new creation.
The answer is yes.
I'd now invite you to partake in the bread, which is Christ's body broken for us, but with
the hope and knowledge that it was resurrected.
In the same way, I invite you to drink the juice, celebrating his victory on the cross while
remembering his blood shed for us for the forgiveness of sins.
Church, I have kept you longer than usual.
I hope that's okay.
Church, I now encourage you to go in the hope and peace of the resurrection of Jesus.
Be the salt and light to the earth as God's representatives of heaven here and now.
Thank you all.
Thank you.